I think it's important to value your portfolio in sats and not US dollars.
What I do is I buy Bitcoin and then anytime it's between.
But here's the trick.
A lot of people think about getting into the market.
They're fine to DCA in.
But when it comes to the selling, people don't ever think about DCAing out.
The ROI of Bitcoin from the bottom.
It's actually tracking the 2016-2017 cycle almost perfectly at this point.
But then I would guess that the Federal Reserve would end quantitative tightening.
Well, you would probably see altcoins outperform Bitcoin.
But in order for the Fed to end quantitative tightening, you have to have a scare in the market first.
But I think this is why the cycle feels different to a lot of people.
This reminds me of, you know, the argument of you and Michael Saylor.
A lot of people that just kind of log on to TradingView and they're like, you know, they'll do, they'll just draw the lines and that's it.
I actually do think a lot of that is useless.
I think the best thing is.
How's it going?
claim the fame if you want success then take a look away
hi ben how's it going
i'm very excited to talk to you today because i refer you as the chart guy and you're very known
for being rational and data driven right i was looking at your youtube channel the about page
and i saw that you have a background in science engineering and programming crazy huh and you
also started into the cryptoverse which is a platform with all the charts and insights for
crypto investors before we dive into all that i want to know who is behind the charts and i want
to start with your story um what were you doing before crypto and before youtube sure so college
i um studied math um kind of first got interested into into crypto and stuff because of of that
background right i took a cryptography class back in like 2011 and i think that was when i first got
interested in the ideas i majored in math minored in physics and then i went to grad school where i got a
a master's in nuclear engineering and then a phd in nuclear engineering so i did several different
like internships i i worked a little bit at like nasa langley in virginia and then a little bit at
nasa johnson space center in houston texas where i know it's a mouthful but basically i programmed like
the lunar rover component of a distributed space simulation uh that was fun and then eventually
i i graduated with my phd my phd uh dissertation was on radiation damage and ceramics using molecular
dynamics and in-situ transmission electron microscopy so i did that and i graduated with my phd in 2018
and then i started a postdoc at the national labs where i basically focused on on high energy density
physics and like equation of state models actually in 2019 uh while i was doing my postdoc that i started
the youtube channel i remember starting it uh the summer of 2019 i had just gone to a conference
where i presented some of my research and after i presented it i decided to start a youtube channel
um talking about crypto why and i i mean at the time that the goal was just uh to to basically help
people like to i don't know like i always found i always found just like plotting some of the different
metrics against each other like really interesting um and also like i'd been burned a lot in the past
of crypto like buying things i probably shouldn't have bought like fomoing in at the tops um i think
we've all sort of done that at some point or another um so you know i i found i had made a lot of mistakes
and i still do make mistakes right i'm not perfect um but yeah i just wanted to like you know make a
make a channel try to help people and um it took off and i i ended up doing the youtube channel
and still doing my full-time job my full-time job at the labs i did i actually got promoted from a
postdoc to a like a senior member of the staff like a scientist and and shortly after getting that
promotion i quit and i i quit my job in 2021 um basically what happened is i i was working on
the youtube stuff and trying to like grow that i was also working on my professional career
and i i quickly just got to the point where i was like i can't do both you know i mean like
at least i can't do both in a good way like i can't give my best to both things right so i have to pick
one or the other when i first started youtube it was just like a side gig i would make like one video
every week or every two weeks you know it wasn't like a big deal and then you know the fed printed
well i guess i started my channel before the fed started to print all that money but um because the
fed printed so much money you know it just made all the markets go up a lot and a lot of attention
came to crypto so then i quit my job in 2021 and i've just been doing this full-time ever since 2021
um so that's the story you drop a lot of big words earlier and i was just nodding like i pretend to
understand okay a guy as smart as you why didn't you pick stocks why crypto so originally i was
interested in stocks and i still am i mean i still have like sizable stock portfolio um i think the
reason why i chose to talk more about crypto was because it felt and i think my view on this is wrong
actually um but at the time it felt like the market was saturated with people talking about
the stock market and i'm like you know there's already a lot of really smart people talking about
the stock market um what what value could i possibly provide you know just by sort of reiterating some of
the main points that people have learned over the last you know several decades uh so i was like well
what if i apply sort of like a or try to apply a rational approach to the markets into the crypto
markets where it's kind of like the wild wild west you know and and it's just everything's really
volatile and no one really knows what they're doing but we're just kind of hoping to get in
and get out and make some money and actually the real thing is when i started my channel i wasn't even
talking about bitcoin because i thought the market was also saturated with bitcoin analysts so i actually
started talking about like like like other cryptocurrencies because i'm like well there's already a thousand
people that talk about bitcoin why do people care what i have to say but your first video was on
ethereum uh well that's the first video that's still public yes oh right okay so small caps
yeah but i mean not not like super like most of them were not that small i mean it was just you know
some some projects back in 2019 i found interesting i mean you know i think probably 10 people watched some
of those videos back then and and some of those projects are are still around today um but i just
decided to focus more on on larger like higher market cap things and as my channel grew i felt like i had
a responsibility to only focus on higher market cap things because the lower market cap stuff you know
you start to be you know i don't know if you you can move the market or not but at some point
you start to question like if i make a video on this is it going to affect the market and i don't really
want to be in that type of situation where i'm like suggesting something that could theoretically
affect the market but things like bitcoin and ethereum like my opinion is is irrelevant over the
you know like it doesn't really matter the market's so much bigger than me so it made it a lot easier
to talk about a lot of kols or youtubers they want to dump on their viewers yeah i mean so i guess
the point is like you know why do people join i mean like why did i start the channel i started to help
people right i actually i truly want to help people not just pretend like i do one of the
things the space really lacks right now or is is people that actually are genuine and aren't just
trying to be like a sellout and and create a meme coin and then like rug their followers you know like
we have enough of that and honestly i i feel like it makes the space somewhat of a joke at times because
like when you know when you talk about crypto to like people that aren't really into it that much
they don't really know that much they're not the the news they're seeing not isn't necessarily like
bitcoin they're basically seeing all these meme coins that are launching and like you know oh
who's what's the latest meme coin and that's what a lot of people think of so i mean hopefully we can
get to a point where the asset class is a little bit more mature it just makes sense to not like
screw people over you know like try to actually help and i think people actually appreciate that i
know a lot of people will will do things and sort of for that for the short-term gain i can't imagine
any of them look back on it and think that they're happy they did it yeah well you seem very rational
and but you said you made some mistakes in the past and you fomoed i want to know what are some
mistakes you've made and have you ever struggled with you know emotional bias yeah absolutely um
i think some mistakes i've made uh include things like bullish for too long in a bull market staying
bearish for too long in a bear market buying altcoins and assuming they're going to go up forever
right now i basically just assume that altcoins are oscillators at best against bitcoin so like
best case scenario they just kind of oscillate in a range most of them don't just go up forever
against bitcoin they might have a cycle or two where they go up against bitcoin but usually they
start to decay against bitcoin over a long enough period of time so i didn't used to think that i mean
i used to think that altcoins could gain on bitcoin for more than just a couple of cycles but i i don't
believe that anymore there could be one or two exceptions out there but for the most part the
market just bleeds back to bitcoin over a long enough period of time and i think that i also used to sort
of value my portfolio in u.s dollars but i think it makes a lot more sense to value it in satoshis like
if you value it in satoshis it makes investing in crypto a lot easier because rather than throw all your
money into like altcoins that are bleeding against bitcoin during this phase of the market cycle like
there are other phases of the cycle where altcoins outperform bitcoin but we haven't really seen that
this cycle for the most part at least not in any durable fashion um so you know i think it's important
to value your portfolio in sats and not u.s dollars and i think you know when when i used to value it in
u.s dollars um it was easier to make emotional decisions because i would you know i watched the price
be cut in half there goes like half my portfolio or you know half my at least net worth in crypto
is just gone but if you value it in terms of satoshis and you kind of operate under the
understanding that bitcoin will generally go up as a function of time then those moves in the market
right if you're if you're watching it and the market drops 50 percent if you just look at your
satoshi valuation you're not going to really see that same thing so it takes a while to sort of train
your mind to to not think in terms of u.s dollars and i think a lot of people say they don't but then
like the minute the market drops 10 all of a sudden they value their portfolio in u.s dollars again um
but i i do think that was that was a mistake you just kind of see things come and go right people
thinking that something's gonna flip bitcoin it hasn't happened in 16 years and i just i don't think
it's gonna happen and if it ever does happen it's probably not anytime soon you know so i think on
any reasonable time scale bitcoin will stay number one and you know anytime people start really talking
about like the flippening uh whether it was for ethereum or for solana it's usually a good time to
to think that it might start to stall out against bitcoin soon and go back the other way so i do think
one other thing is and i still struggle this sometimes i think like people should be willing to
you know admit they're wrong or or change their mind about the market if the market is telling
them something different i think sometimes the mistakes i've made were just not listening to the
market like refusing to see the market in any other way than what i thought made the most amount of
sense um but again over a long enough period of time the market humbles us all and earlier you said
sometimes you hold a coin too long but now you have all the charts what charts are you looking at
to indicate let's say the top a few days ago the market dropped and people are panicking
they were like that was the top and i missed the top some people are buying the dip but it was very
confusing are there any charts that you look at so like here's one chart that i i look at a lot
it's basically just like this risk metric uh of bitcoin um and and essentially whenever it goes to the
lower wristbands like this is i'm isolating sort of the zero to point two wristbands whenever it goes
down there it's usually a good time to buy bitcoin that doesn't mean that the price can't go down
after it goes into that wristband but as long as you have a long enough time horizon you're generally
okay and then selling when it gets to the higher wristbands can often make a lot of sense but the
reality is is no one actually knows where the top's going to be um and so what i do
is i'm looking at the risk metric this way so i'm taking the color code out of it and just plotting it
what i do is i buy bitcoin below 0.5 risk um or 0.4 depending on like what risk tolerance i want to
take on for that period of time or that cycle um and i i buy anytime it's below that level
and then anytime it's between 0.5 and 0.6 risk i don't do anything like i don't buy it but i also
don't sell it you know it's like it's a little heated for me to want to buy it but i also don't
really think it's high enough to justify selling any of it either but above 0.6 i do start to think
that profit taking can make sense but here's the trick you know a lot of people think about
getting into the market they're fine to dcan but when it comes to the to selling people don't ever
think about dca now they just want to time the top exactly they want to time the top exactly and and
then go on with their lives but the hard part is if you let's say you sell everything at 0.65 risk
and then the market goes up to 0.9 risk then you you miss out on another two to three x move
but if it goes to 0.6 to 0.7 risk and you don't sell anything then like 2019 you could be left with
some regrets like you know watching the market and drop 70 something percent wishing you had sold some
so what i do essentially the strategy that i found works for me is anytime it goes above 0.6 risk i will
sell one tenth of the bitcoin that i'm willing to sell now i have more bitcoin than that but like
there's some amount of bitcoin that i just won't ever sell and and the reason for that is because
while i have a lot of great models or i think they're great i also recognize that all models are
wrong and some are useful right i mean i don't think any model out there is going to tell you what's going
to happen in the market precisely um so what i would say is you know by selling a small portion
one tenth between say like the 0.6 0.7 risk level i can still be happy if the price goes up because i
still have nine tenths of my bitcoin you know i still have 90 of it but there's also a small part
of me that's still okay if you get a dip because i you know i have i have some cash on hand i could
use it to buy bitcoin if in fact there is a correction and then if it goes to say like the 0.7
to 0.8 risk ban then i would then sell two tenths right so 20 percent of the bitcoin and then you know
0.8 to 0.9 i would sell 30 percent and then 0.9 to one i would sell 40 percent right the rest of
whatever i'm willing to sell now again at all times i'll still own something um and i remember last
cycle uh you know basically if you follow this strategy and and and what i did basically was
just selling 87 percent of my bitcoin by that first peak you know and it was painful because
you know i think i was mostly out back then around like 58k 59k and then the market like slowly went
up for another like month or two definitely making me like a little concerned you know um so like
there's the emotional part right i was like looking at the model and i'm like it it it seems like this
should be a subtle top but the price just keeps going a little little bit higher um but then ultimately
you can see what happened like the market eventually came came crashing back down so
this and this was back when a lot of people were calling for like 300k right you know 300k bitcoin
back in 2021 was a popular narrative and it and it certainly felt like i was going to get left behind
by parting with 87 percent of the bitcoin but you know you fast forward a year later and you're like
actually you know it made a lot of sense so the reason why i like this is because there's so much
news all the time um and it can be confusing as to figure out like i mean i think the news is
interesting and i follow it but i don't really think the news is like the best thing to use for
investing right because like okay it's always changing and and and oftentimes you know when bad
news is coming out the market's going up and when good news is coming out the market's going down
you know so it doesn't always work how people think um and there's there's other risk metrics as well
um one of my one of my other favorite ones i mean i have like on-chain risk metrics um
so basically like this just takes all the on-chain data for bitcoin which is kind of cool because
bitcoin has all this on-chain data that you can look at right like the pure multiple the mbrv score
the mbrv z score transaction fees terminal price minor cap to thermo cap uh and then like this so this
is the minor cap to thermo cap and then market cap to thermo cap and so basically if you look at at all of
them and you create risk metrics for all of them it looks something like that which is kind of
confusing but then if you average them out into one risk metric it looks like that and so it it really
does help identify you know major lows in the market and then it also tells you when the market is
getting somewhat heated you know um so this is essentially what i use to navigate crypto right risk
metrics i just stick to those and i i mean as far as bitcoin is concerned i just stick to the risk
metrics when it comes to altcoins it's a little bit more nuanced but with bitcoin this is what i use
and the ultimate goal is to accumulate more bitcoin right so you were just mentioning when to sell but
um how do you identify when to buy like when is the bottom yeah so for that it's just basically
going back to whenever whenever it goes below i mean really anytime it goes like below 0.3 risk or 0.2 risk
it's usually pretty close to a low a major low right um you know there's other interesting charts as well
like you could look at like the running one year roi bitcoin and anytime it goes down to around 20 percent
from a year ago uh that tends to be a major cycle bottom right so that's another chart that you can look
yeah that tends to be pretty close um you there's other charts as well uh so we actually have some
bottoming indicators on the website um so like another one could be um here's the supply and profit
and loss i mean it looks pretty compelling right you can see that cycle peaks occur you know when these
diverge and they've been diverged for a while cycle bottoms occur um you know when they cross each other
right like so if you were to take um let's say like a 30-day moving average anytime these moving
averages are crossing each other that usually is like the cycle bottom right so that's another chart
you can use um there's a few more i mean you could you could look at at the terminal price and the
balance price so like the terminal price is where normally bitcoin tops out at anytime it goes below the
balance price that's where the market bottoms at so in this case whenever the price to bitcoin goes
below this orange line that tends to be the cycle bottom and you can see that it tagged it right
there in november 2022 um so there's a lot of charts like this that you can use to at least give you an
idea of what's going on um the mbrv z score is a good metric to use right anytime it goes below zero
it tends to be near a cycle bottom as well um i mean i could i could certainly go on for a while
there are a lot of charts like this though i mean even the pure multiple is is a decent chart for
identifying cycle bottoms right anytime it goes below 0.4 that tends to be a major low in the market
right now it's at 1.04 um so i i think like i think there's enough charts out there to get a good idea
when a cycle bottom is in place um in fact you could argue that bottoms are actually a lot easier
to deal with than tops because i think i think as humans we all want to remain optimistic right i think
it's just in our nature to like you know be optimistic we want to be optimistic and and
because the fed's never going to stop printing money there's no reason that you know assets like
bitcoin can't always eventually go higher even if they do go through bear markets so normally the cycle
bottoms occur sort of around the end of midterm years in the united states right so 2022 2018
2014 and so far cycle peaks have occurred at the end of post-haven years 2013 2017 2021
but if you look at history in the stock market while the bottoms tend to be pretty consistent as
to when they occur the tops can be all over the place so i actually think bottoms are easier to buy
into than tops are to sell into because i feel like a lot of people get really greedy at tops and
and you also you also don't really want to be the person like telling people that the you know that
the market crashed you know because like there's one of two outcomes right if you're right people are
upset because they lose money if they don't sell right if they just hold on to it then they're upset
and and you don't want to like be seen as you know being like well i told you so um because it's not
really a fun place to be and if you're wrong then you're the person that was calling for the crash
and you got left behind right so you don't it's not really fun being in that position so i think
bottoms are actually easier to deal with than tops because greed you know dealing with greed is a
really difficult thing are you selling now is it a top i think that in this case so if we go back and
look at the risk metric i think that the market has been a little heated um because it did go back
above 0.6 right it did go back about 0.6 and i did sell some over here in that first i thought it was
sort of a mid-cycle top uh and the market would cool off for about six to nine months so that did work
out um this i mean it's a little heated i i think you you could justify um a small portion but it's
still not as high as you would expect it to go for it to truly be a a cycle top now there always is a
risk of of a left translated cycle where the peak occurs a lot earlier than people are expecting
um i hope it's a right translate it's like right i hope that the market is able to go higher uh
especially later on this year but um late last year i did say for you know for a while that we
could see a significant top january 20th and the reason for that and so far that has been the high
i'm not saying it's the high but it's been at least a significant high and the reason for the
january 20th there's a number of reasons uh one you know you basically are pricing in the new
administration coming in um the market is basically believing in the strategic bitcoin reserve you had
gary ginsler resigning that week so it almost felt like perfection was getting priced in right and then
once the once the new administration took over the market de-risked because now it's like all right
what's actually going to happen right are we going to get a strategic reserve or are we not and what
timeline is that going to be on we could get one but what if we don't get one until say 2028 you know
like there's no guarantee we have to get it this year um so i do think it makes sense that that
january 20th was at least a local top i don't really think at this point you know there's a ton of
evidence to suggest that it has to be like v top if it's going to play out like that i think we would
get a lot of warning ahead of time but uh sometimes when the market gets too heated and and the froth
boils to the surface right all the meme coin garbage it you know takes over there's always a chance that
you could get a left translated cycle where the peak occurs earlier than people are actually thinking
i do think every cycle will throw his curveballs the one thing that i i sort of go back to
sometimes um not because i think it's necessarily going to happen but just because i i have to imagine
people 25 years ago felt the same way if you go back and and look at when the qqq launched uh this was
you know the basket of tech stocks back during the dot-com era um you know it had a really strong rally
as well and the rally lasted exactly 54 weeks from when the etf launched 54 weeks and and then you can
see there was a pretty big drop after that but the market was still able to go up for a while right
it just it resolved into a lower high but what's fascinating about the qqq comparison and the reason
why i think about it is because when it launched it was right around 48 48 and then it topped at around
120 now when bitcoin's etf launched right if you go over to to uh bitcoin
the etf launched right here on this on that wick right there so january 8th right so the reason i
also suggested january 20th could be at least a local top was 54 weeks later is exactly january 20th
which is when that oh wow which is exactly what which is exactly when the qqq sort of topped out
now the markets back then were actually a lot more insane than they are now right like it's not
they're not at the same levels as they were back then which is why i i think it is somewhat foolish
to make the exact same comparison um and actually one way to view that is if you look at at say like
the s p 500 divided by the money supply you'll notice that right now we're at this level so we're
at we're at if you look at so so this is this is the s p again divided by m2 the money supply and if
you look at this the level that the s p is at right now is the same level that was at in 1998
not the dot com not march of 2000 so you can see that there was a correction in the market around
this level right there was a correction but ultimately the market did actually go higher
so that's why i was sort of a little cautious with bitcoin after inauguration not because i think it has
to be the cycle top um but just because you know there's going to be some de-risking going into
inauguration also the people that bought the spot etf january 8th they've now reached long-term capital
gains territory right now they can sell and they don't have to pay as much in taxes so i figured
that could be a headwind for bitcoin for a little while i think at this point though when you look at
at bitcoin in general you know this cycle has been crazy like we've had spot etfs we've had you know
president president the president talking about bitcoin right i mean in a positive way that's never
really happened before but despite everything despite all these comparisons to the qqq and and
you know yield curve inversion and all that other stuff if you look at the roi of bitcoin from the
bottom it's actually tracking the 2016 2017 cycle almost perfectly at this point you know and i mean at
this point in the 2016 cycle bitcoin was up about the same amount that it's up this cycle and so i go
back to to sort of that and and i try to look at this chart to sort of keep myself in check and then
the other chart that i look at to give me some perspective on the market is this chart which is
the total market cap of crypto and right now it still seems like it's right around what i would call
sort of the fair value right i think the fair value of the asset class according to this chart again all
models are wrong but according to this chart the fair value of the asset class is around 3.4 trillion
and we're currently at around 3.2 trillion so i don't really necessarily believe that it's nearly
as heated as as the dot-com era um i think it's possible that you could get a pullback in the market
that makes people think it's over you know like maybe you get sort of a drop back to back to this level
here um and then a big bounce off of that if you go if you go back to the qqq you know when it first
got that drop right there the structure of the market was a lot different right it it looks a lot
different than bitcoin like bitcoin was you know it put in this lower high structure and then eventually
it broke through the qqq it was sort of like a higher high structure um it looks a lot different but
what's interesting is the price level that the qqq went down to on that wick was 63 now if you look
at bitcoin if it were to go back to this trend line right here you know it would correspond to around
that same level so you know i think worst case scenario in the short term like absolute worst case
would be you know a drop but i think there would be a massive bounce off of any level that that came
down here and then one final thing i actually think the the 2016 2017 cycle has been really really
relevant uh and and so one thing to consider and i remember this from from the 2017 cycle it was kind
of scary when it happened but in sort of in january of 2017 so january post-having year there was a
correction and and basically what happened was bitcoin retested its prior high from the prior year
right so from the halving year it tested its high i'm sure a lot of people thought it was over and then
the market continued higher so you could argue that there's a chance that history repeats and if it does
it could mean not going back down to that trend line but maybe just retesting the high from 2024
2024 you know maybe it just drops down here everyone thinks the cycle's over and then it just gets
another move up um and and hopefully we get a peak in q4 of of the post-having year we get our normal
midterm year bear market for whatever reason and then we just keep on on you know the the asset class
just continues to grow um so those are my general thoughts right now on on the market i mean i i think
there's a chance you could get a correction by bitcoin and if you do though right here's a key
thing if you do get a correction by bitcoin what would likely happen is you would see a bigger
correction in the altcoin market kind of like we've been seeing over the last few weeks um but then i
would guess that the federal reserve would end quantitative tightening and then from that point on in the
whatever's left of the market cycle you would probably see altcoins outperform bitcoin
but in order for the fed in quantitative tightening you have to have a scare in the market first right
otherwise they have no really great reason to end quantitative tightening so until that time you know
i sort of just defer to just keep the crypto portfolio bitcoin heavy until there's a reason for the fed to
nqt right once once quantitative tightening ends that's where alt bitcoin pairs will likely start to do
well and you know i don't know how many people um how many of your subscribers follow the bitcoin
dominance chart but i mean bitcoin dominance has been going higher for years right so i mean it really
goes to show that sticking with bitcoin is is really a good thing especially until the fed pivots from
quantitative tightening to potentially quantitative easing and the last thing is that in in in last
cycle bitcoin dominance did not top it topped right here and it topped exactly when the fed went from
quantitative tightening to quantitative easing right that's when bitcoin dominance topped and so we
might see the same exact thing happen this cycle like what exactly should we look at is is is reducing
the size of their balance sheet right they're they're they're basically letting um these things mature and
they're not they're not like rebuying anything they're just letting they're letting their assets roll
off from their balance sheet and so what's happening is you can see that their balance sheet this blue line
is dropping now when the when when it's dropping when it's dropping if you look at at altcoins on their
bitcoin pairs right so this chart is total three the altcoin market minus usdt stable coin divided by the
market cap of bitcoin what you'll notice is that they tend to bottom out whenever the altcoin market
is equivalent to 25 of bitcoin's market cap and altcoins top out whenever they collectively reach
a market cap that is basically parity with bitcoin right so whenever the altcoin market cap total is
the same market cap as bitcoin that's where the altcoin market tops out against bitcoin and it bottoms
out whenever the altcoin market is worth 25 of bitcoin's market cap so what i'm just saying is that
you know until we and you can see that alt bitcoin pairs last cycle they bottomed exactly when that
pivot by the fed occurred right down here alt bitcoin pairs are bleeding here the fed went into
quantitative easing and then altcoins started to go up against bitcoin so my guess is that the same
thing's happening this cycle right alt bitcoin pairs continue to bleed they actually just put on a new low
this week um and i think the reason you saw this low is because last week or two weeks ago whenever
it was jerome powell came out and said no you know we're not stopping right we're going to continue
quantitative tightening and i think a lot of people were hoping that with a new administration
that there would be some type of pressure for quantitative tightening to end turns out there hasn't been
and so we got another another drop by altcoins against bitcoin so what i'm suggesting is that
the only way to see altcoins go up against bitcoin collectively i mean not the only way but like this
is the narrative i've been sticking with for the last three years and it's worked out um but the way i
see it is that the way for altcoins to do well against bitcoin is for the fed to end quantitative
tightening um which they have not done but in order for the fed to end quantitative tightening
you have to have a drop in the markets because otherwise the fed just has no really great reason
to end quantitative tightening um right so until that time occurs you're probably better off with
bitcoin than altcoins because if bitcoin goes down alts will drop more and if bitcoin goes and if alts go
up it's only because bitcoin went up first right so that's why i think bitcoin dominance is important
because that allows people to just basically stick with the king and watch everything else bleed back
to bitcoin until we reach the point in the cycle where altcoins start to outperform bitcoin
but a lot of people argue that this cycle is different because we have so many altcoins now
and people just pump meme coins from pump.fun and i want to know if you think the four-year cycle
this will still hold like for example the waterfall of bitcoin ethereum big cap small cap and then meme
coin is likely the top does it still um work so when i think about four-year cycles i mostly think about
when the bottoms are right so i think the the four-year cycle mostly refers to the bottoms and the
next the next major low should be the end of 2026 that's what i would say i'd say the next major low
should be the end of 2026 no matter what happens this year whether we get you know whether bitcoin
rallies up to 150k 200k later this year we'll probably still have a major low in late 2026 if the
top is in and we're unfortunate and we get a left translated cycle you still would likely still you
would likely still see the market do relatively well for most of the year it wouldn't become obvious
until q4 when the market normally goes up if the market goes down instead um as far as meme coins
and whatnot you know i know a lot of people call this the meme coin super cycle and whatnot but
you know if you look at this chart here is others divided by bitcoin and others is everything outside of
the top 10 at least what trading detracts which is like a couple hundred coins um and others
has been dropping against bitcoin since 2022 began so i know there's this narrative that it's a meme
coin super cycle but i think what's really happening is these meme coins are just dropping against bitcoin
right they're just dropping and and i think a lot of people are just kind of watching their their
the satoshi valuation of their portfolio evaporate because they keep losing all their money in these
meme coins and they would have just been better off sticking with bitcoin now i'm not suggesting that no
one has made money in meme coins i know some meme coins have done phenomenally well right and a lot of
people have made a lot of money right it's absolutely true that that's the case but i i think with the
meme coins it's it's ultimately a zero-sum game right if someone is making a ton of money it means
there's a lot of people losing a lot of money um that's kind of how i would i would view the meme
coin market because over a long enough period of time a lot of these altcoins do eventually go to
zero asymptotically against bitcoin you know it could take five years right which is a much longer
time frame than any of the people trading these meme coins care about so you're not really going to
convince them that it's important but um i do think that you know this has been going on a really
really long time and my guess is that it's not going to change until the fed changes monetary
policy but i mean i look as far as the cycle stuff goes i think the biggest you know the the biggest
dangers when people think this time is different and so far it's been the same in terms of monetary
policy and then in terms of market cycle roi bitcoin looks basically how it always looks at this point
in the cycle i think if you do get a scare in the markets it'll just be a reason to diversify some
into altcoins if the fed can pivot otherwise i think you're probably just most people are probably
just better off with bitcoin um until that time comes earlier you mentioned people bought etf on
january the 8th and they sold because they want to avoid tax what was that about so i'm not i don't
really have any evidence for that i'm i don't like i don't have any evidence that anyone specifically
bought and then sold what i'm suggesting is that if there are people in the united states that bought
january 8th of 2024 then there's two categories right so if you sell within 12 months the taxes you
have to pay on your profits is higher so if you wait a year and then sell you pay a lot less taxes
so i'm just suggesting i'm just suggesting there could be some investors out there that bought bitcoin
and then they watched they bought the etf they watched it go up 3x about because they bought it
you know around 40k 45k and then it went up to 109k if they watched it go up 3x and they were in
long-term capital gains territory maybe some of those people elected to to take some profits right and
then that could be contributing to some of the headwinds that we're seeing right now but i mean in
the short term bitcoin's actually doing the same thing it did last year around this time um you know
basically it moved up in in october and november right here same same kind of thing and then it
started moving again in in february and march so i i hope i hope that that bitcoin can just follow that
path and and kind of continue what it did last year but you know there certainly are some warning signs
that it might not and and one of those could be you know uh i think about like the blue chips right
bitcoin is the blue chip of the cryptoverse in the stock market you could argue that nvidia
has been the blue chip and nvidia has been doing really really well so last year in in january
nvidia was skyrocketing uh while bitcoin was flat right it was it was going up while bitcoin was flat
and then eventually bitcoin followed right this time this year it's kind of the opposite right bitcoin is flat
but nvidia is going down so it it makes me wonder if if there's going to be a scare at some point in
the next few months that's going to allow the fed to pivot and to qe and then it doesn't mean that
bitcoin can't go up it just means that the gains like the the rest of the gains for the cycle will
not be as good for bitcoin as it might be for some other cryptocurrencies right that have been beaten
down over the last um several years there's actually a really interesting chart i could show you a lot of
people feel like this cycle is different than than last cycle and it's kind of one of those things
where like if you look at bitcoin's roi from the low it looks the same as it always looked right so why
do people feel that way well a lot of people joined crypto in 2020 and this chart here is called the
advanced decline index so it basically shows you it basically helps you figure out are more assets
going up or are more assets going down right on against the for the price so in 2020 when a lot of
people joined crypto you can see that this line this orange line was going up meaning more assets were
going up than were going down right i mean you could basically pick any altcoin and it was going up
you know in 2020 because of all the money printing but this adi the advanced decline index since 2022
began really since november 2021 has been going down right it's been going down so i think the reason
why this bull market feels different to a lot of people is because bitcoin and a few altcoins are
responsible for a majority of the gains right yeah and and a lot of altcoins are really struggling
but you'll notice that last cycle the eight the advanced decline index was also dropping and it
did not bottom until after the fed ended quantitative tightening right it once the fed ended qt it was
shortly after that that this index started to go back up we just haven't seen that this cycle and it's
weird because it's taking a lot longer than it took last cycle but i think this is why the cycle feels
different to a lot of people's because they keep putting all their money in these altcoins expecting for
them to go up like 10x 20x like last cycle and they're just not seeing those same types of gains
but they're seeing bitcoin go up you know um and so i think a lot of people kind of got left behind
because they didn't just stick with bitcoin so can i say that you know we might see some more correction
but don't sell your altcoins yet i think the way to think about it is this i think that if there is a
correction in the market right so so right now no one knows right absolutely no one knows no one has
a crystal ball we have to accept that no one knows what's going to happen i would say that at this point
in time until qt is over bitcoin is a better play from a risk adjusted returns point of view if there
is a drop in the market let's say in the first half of the year i do think that whatever this cycle has
left in it from that point on at least through the end of this year and maybe early 2026 you would
likely see altcoins outperform bitcoin but in order to get that you have to have a drop in the market
first so for me what that what the way that what that's me what that's meant for me is that i've
basically kept my portfolio mostly bitcoin it's not entirely bitcoin but mostly bitcoin i think there's a
good middle ground and there's a tool uh modern portfolio theory so this is something that was
developed you know decades ago for for you know things like the stock market and whatnot but if you
look at this it basically you can plot out your risk adjusted returns for various portfolios and so
for a portfolio consisting of bitcoin ethereum and just say us dollars let's say you want to have some
us dollars in case there's a dip what's a good percentage right what's a good percentage so in
this case based on data going back to 2015 this would suggest that the portfolio that maximizes your
sortino ratio which is a ratio that does not punish positive volatility which i think is better than the
sharp ratio which does is 58 bitcoin 12 eth and then 30 us dollars right is what it's saying so basically
you know it still makes sense to have this exposure 70 exposure to the market but if there is a drop
then you know the worst feeling is when the market drops 30 percent and you have nothing to buy it with
right um so at least that gives you a hedge now if you take us dollars out of this
and calculate it with just bitcoin and eth it says 83 bitcoin and 17 percent eth but for me
i haven't even gone with that i'm more so in this camp right here 93 bitcoin 7 because that's the
portfolio that minimizes your volatility and i've been focused more so on minimizing my volatility
and just allowing myself to preserve the satoshi valuation of my portfolio right so that's kind of where
i am right now 93 7 um it might actually be exactly that i don't know i mean it varies on a day-to-day
basis based on what the eth bitcoin ratio is doing i i think that eth is really close to bottoming out
against bitcoin um like really really close if it hasn't already but i do respect that until the fed
pivots eth could still go lower against bitcoin a lot of people would replace eth with solana this cycle
so what's interesting about solana is it's tracking e bitcoin it's just two and a half two and a half
years behind um now i will say solana has done really really well this cycle like absolutely it's
done really well a lot of people made a lot of money um i hope it has a bright future i mean i think that
maybe if people can move away from like you know the meme coin stuff and focus on like things that
actually matter and you know utility i think it could have a bright future um but and one of the
things you look for for alt bitcoin pairs uh for when they're going to rally is you look at double
bottoms against bitcoin right so with solana um you can see that it had a double bottom against bitcoin
right here and so that's usually a good sign for an altcoin whenever you get this double bottom
that's usually the bottom for a while eth bitcoin did the same exact thing right so if you look at
eth bitcoin the cycle before so not this cycle but the cycle before it had a double bottom right and then
it had this rally now here's what's interesting about eth bitcoin and compared to sole bitcoin is that
it's almost the exact same chart it's just that sole bitcoin is behind two and a half years so watch
this so if you go to the eth bitcoin chart and you take a price range from this peak here go down
eth bitcoin dropped about 89 percent right in that in that bear market right 89 percent
sole bitcoin if you look at the same exact thing right the same chart or the same price range down from
this peak down it was also exactly an 89 percent drop right it's the same drop now after an 89 percent
drop then sole bitcoin double bottoms eth bitcoin double bottoms right it was the same thing and so
what's fascinating about this is it continued to play out right it continued to play out so look at
eth bitcoin you'll see that it had this higher low structure that eventually broke down right here
right so it was putting in these higher higher lows and then eventually it broke down and everyone thought
it was over right everyone thought it was over and then the merge happened right and then eth bitcoin
shot back up and then it was just a slow and painful bleed now look at sole bitcoin it's the same thing
right so you basically have the same thing you have this higher low structure right you have a higher
low structure and then it broke down everyone thought it was over and then president trump launched a meme
coin on solana um and then you saw sole bitcoin go back up so what's interesting is if you go look at
this on a log scale and take eth bitcoin on a log scale and if you just simply take a
bar pattern if you take a bar pattern this is by the way this is sole bitcoin not sole usd
right you could so solana bitcoin could go down but solana usd could still go up if bitcoin's going up
right so i think a lot of people need to remember because like during this entire bleed by eth against
bitcoin eth usd has actually been going up not down it's just that bitcoin has been going up quicker
so a lot of people if if you're trained to think in terms of us dollars and you see a chart that looks
like this like oh that means the the assets crashing but if you overlay its usd valuation
um you can see that it's actually been going up so again bitcoin has a way of of sort of lifting
you know the different um the different boats right it has a way of lifting all the boats
and and you can see how eth bitcoin is diverging from eth usd but again i digress the thing i wanted
to say was that if you look at at eth bitcoin and you take a bar pattern from this top to to where it
is now and we just copy that and then paste it you know somewhere on this chart and we just sort of
pull it out i mean you can see how similar the chart is right where you get your yeah like you get your
bear market you get your double bottom and then goes back up and then everyone calls for the flipping
and then it just goes into this massive secondary distribution and then it comes back down now look
if that happens it's not the end for solana i mean i i think that when i say all coins are oscillators at
best i truly believe it so with eth i don't think it's dead i don't i just think that until quantitative
tightening is over it's going to bleed against bitcoin but here's the thing don't look at the eth
don't look at the eth bitcoin price ratio look at the market cap ratio
and you'll see that it oscillates right it goes from the top of the range to the bottom of the range
and when it's up here people call for the flipping and when it's down here people say the eth is dead
right so um you could see something happen similar with solana where it oscillates within a range now
look at the sole market cap divided by the bitcoin market cap and you'll see the exact same thing
right it's it we're in a range right we're in a range and anytime it's down here people call or you
know people say it's dead and then it's up here people call for the flipping right they call for
the flipping up here so when it's up here no one can ever think about it going back down here when
it's down here no one can ever think about it going back up so i would argue that the sole bitcoin
chart to me looks like eth bitcoin two and a half years ago and that it could very well bleed
bleed into 2026 but if it does bleed into 2026 that doesn't mean that it can't do well again in
say 2027 2028 2029 i just think that a lot of these cryptocurrencies oscillate against bitcoin
and whenever you're at an whenever you're at an extreme no one ever wants to believe that it could
ever reverse course but i think it's important to try to remain objective and by the way i mean just
to be clear i know some people out there might hold solana and might not like this view so i will say
this like there are times when an asset looks like this and it looks like it won't go higher
and then it does okay so there's not it's not like there's a guarantee that i'm right about that
um there are times i think like inj bitcoin earlier this year sort of had you know you can see that it
looked like it could have not gone above that level right you could have argued that it was an
oscillator as well um and that it wouldn't go above that level and then you had this massive breakout
but then you know a few you know a year or two later you can see that it was just sort of a fake
out and it just came right back down um but sometimes you will get that and then it sort of
proves you wrong but i think in general the soul bitcoin chart looks like eph bitcoin to me
so if i were to take that explanation and let's say i hold soul i might consider selling soul soon
to buy eth so that's a really loaded question because the soul eth chart is is actually pretty
crazy um the soul eth chart so solana has been outperforming ethereum a lot okay and i don't know
honestly i don't even know if i would make that conclusion um i think you could
it could work out right i mean this might just be sort of this a wedge right that that it's going up
into and then eventually it just breaks down but the thing about that that i that doesn't really sit
well with me is that who knows how long that's going to last i mean you know it's already been
going on for years who's to say it can't go on for another year right um so i don't i don't i
wouldn't necessarily say that's the like the best decision it it could work out really really well
i think the more obvious thing is um is is soul bitcoin but even in that case right even in that
case if it if it follows eth bitcoin it could still stay up here for the rest of the year before
dropping back down right it doesn't have to immediately drop and in fact if you look at at
eth bitcoin after it got that breakdown right after eth bitcoin got that that breakdown in um in the
summer of 2022 right it didn't really break down below that level until a year and a half later
right so there's always a chance that like soul bitcoin doesn't truly break down until 2026 you know
um and i mean it could make sense considering that it is a post-halving year and normally altcoins
outperform bitcoin in post-halving years right if you look at at bitcoin dominance um 12 month candles
the only years where dominance really goes down is this year right that the post-halving years 2017
2021 and maybe 2025 but the trick is the only way you're going to see that drop is for the to give the
fat a reason to pivot and you don't get a reason to pivot until there's a drop in the market so
i'm not suggesting that like you know people should go make any like rash trades based on this chart
because you could have made the same argument a year and a half ago right and still bitcoin sell at
the same valuation what i would say though is you know if you're if you're looking to put money into
something and you don't know what to put it in i think because solana against bitcoin is at sort of a
range high i think it makes more sense to put it in bitcoin over solana not necessarily to go
sell your solana for bitcoin if that makes sense right um that way if if the market you know if
you're if you put it in if you just dca into bitcoin and this goes down you'll be happy that you
increased your bitcoin holdings um over solana and if it goes up then at least you didn't sell your
solana so i mean a lot of investing is sort of hedging your bets and not just going all out on one view
we're looking at the charts but i am imagining the day when trump says there is a bitcoin reserve
and bitcoin is just going to shoot up and everyone's saying that you know we are not ready for that and
it's not priced in um and this reminds me of you know the argument of you and michael say right i know
you don't care microstrategy doesn't care i guess my issue is is people are looking at these things
and debating them but if i told you the currency was going to collapse by 90 next tuesday
wouldn't it be more material to point out to people that the currency is going to collapse by 90
next tuesday than to have them study the last 10 years of trading of a lot of complicated i don't
think it has to be black and white it doesn't have to be one or the other that was one of the very
first video i've seen of you and i i have to say you're very ballsy so basically what happened from
what i remember was um you were saying that all the charts represent you know the past and its
statistics right but he was arguing that it cannot predict the future and what happened there
so basically i mean and and for the record i mean this was basically at the 2021 all-time highs when
we did this interview and you know i was i i had these models that suggested that the the
like you know the the peak was really close to being in you know um and this was when bitcoin was
like 60k right so it's not a really popular view to be promoting it's not like i didn't think bitcoin
could go higher i i did think it could go higher um and so did he i think his argument was just
that there's no reason to look at these charts because everything is different and and it's
going to be you know like the cycle is going to be different this time you know all the models are
wrong um and and and i do agree to a large extent that models are often wrong where i got into a big
disagreement with him was i didn't really see that what i was doing was any different than what he was
doing right so basically i was using these charts to say bitcoin's likely going to go higher
in a visual form right i was looking at it visually right looking at things like the running one year
roi or the roi from the cycle low or you know whatever it was like i was looking at it from a
visual perspective and he's sitting and he was basically saying like you know uh that stuff doesn't
matter now to a large extent i agree with that i i don't really think you can look at the past
to predict the future the reason we got into an argument was because i just kind of argued like
how is it any different than what he was doing where he was basically saying bitcoin's gone up 100
this year and 100 last year so it's going to go up 100 next year right i was saying i'm doing the same
exact thing just in a visual format and even today when he's publishing all this stuff about bitcoin
and by the way i mean sailor has done way more for the industry than i have um i just think that
it was you know i just thought at the time and i i think i probably wouldn't get into the same
argument with him now right i probably would just defer and not not go down that route um i think i've
grown up a little bit since then so i think probably 90 of the reason we got in an argument was because
of me not him um and me just wanting to like stand up for my but again i think at this point i
wouldn't i wouldn't even try uh but i i will say that i just i just think about when i when i look
at what he's doing and he's he's often talking on twitter about how great bitcoin's returns have been
right i mean how often do you see that right he talks about you know their roi like you know
bitcoins outperformed the entire s&p 500 and my argument was just i'm doing the exact same thing
that you are i'm just visualizing it you know um rather than just saying it i'm visualizing it and
and i think we kind of disagreed there so that was where it came from again i don't hold anything
against him again he's done more for bitcoin than i ever i ever could imagine to do that was where
that was where it came from and have you spoken after that not really i mean a little bit um i think
i briefly saw him uh at at his party in in um a new year's eve party in miami um but i i mean i think
i spoke two words to him right um that was about it i i think i i didn't you know i i did invite him
to a party i was throwing back in like 2022 or 2023 and we we talked a little bit but that was it so
we've never really talked about that my my guess is he doesn't even remember who i am right so um i
don't really think it matters to him or he cares he i doubt he remembers that conversation because he
does you know he does a million of these conversations um if i were not i i haven't seen any that disagreed
with him yeah i think but i i think like i almost sometimes wonder if it was a misunderstanding
because like i think maybe he thought i was just like using trading view or something like i don't
think he realized i have like other stuff than like just because there's a lot of people that
just kind of log on to trading view and they're like you know they'll do they'll just draw the
lines like they'll just draw the lines and that's it what i would say and again i actually do think a
lot of that is useless i think the best thing is momentum i think momentum is the best technical
analysis and what i mean by that is assets that are going up are more likely to go up than assets
that are not going up right so a lot of people will try to sell an asset that's doing well for
an asset that's not doing well in the hopes that the one that's not doing well will start doing better
but most of the time there is a reason why that other asset was doing well and it continues to do
well and there's a reason the other asset was going down and it just continues going down so i
believe in momentum and i i think a lot of this stuff is as i say dubious speculation right no one
actually knows i just thought that you know some of this other stuff right like modern portfolio theory
based on classical simulations going back in the stock market a lot of hedge funds use that kind
of stuff to navigate markets and and really just looking at like you know cycle roi like i thought
i thought that that had some value to it i feel like if we really hashed it out i don't really think
we would disagree um i just think that you know i i get my argument was just how is it any different
than saying these are the returns for bitcoin last year so therefore it's going to keep doing well
i was just visualizing it made it one of the best interviews i think so congratulations
um you've made a lot of charts so i mean we were talking about some optimistic views and then
sometimes you're like however but there's this other chart that says differently so for a new
person coming into crypto what are some charts that i must start with so i mean again like that's the
thing like you know it's always about hedging your views but i don't exactly what you said right like
there's this that looks good but there's this that looks a little like you know what if it does that
like what if it follows the qqq again there's a lot of what ifs i don't concern myself with the what
ifs i don't really concern myself if there is a strategic bitcoin reserve i just look at the risk and
i'm like you know at this time at this point in time the risk on bitcoin is 0.578 right it's 0.578
so it's a little it's a little high for me to want to go like bet the family farm you know because
like there's a chance that bitcoin just sells off back to 70 or 80k um but it's also it's also not at
like 0.9 right like if we were sitting here right now and bitcoin was at 0.95 risk i would be telling
people i would say it's time to run for the hills because it's going to crash right but it's not
there and i don't know when it's going to go there it's more so i think about it like this no one exactly
knows when it's going to go above 0.8 risk or below 0.2 we don't we can't know i mean in march of 2020
it's not like any of us knew that the market was going to crash right um no one knows when it happens
it's just that if you ever find yourself at a point in the cycle where the risk is above 0.8
or is below 0.2 then i think you should act accordingly right so if it's above 0.8
it means it's time to sell if it's below 0.2 it means it's time to buy if you look at the amount of
time we spend in each wristband what you'll notice is that we spend very little time in those higher
wristbands right so a lot of people think that when you get there it's going to stay there forever
but in reality that highest wristband the 0.9 to 1 wristband in in all of bitcoin's history
it's only been in that wristband for 18 days throughout all 16 years 18 days so again there's
always a lot of what ifs but i'm just saying if sometime later this cycle bitcoin is in the 0.9
to 1 wristband it's probably time to run for the hills and forget about all the narratives that
people are trying to sell at the same time in either you know if in 2026 or at some point
we see another bear market and bitcoin you know is in the 0.1 wristband or the 0.1 to 0.2 wristband
just know that that's the opportunity right that's normally where bitcoin carves out carves out those
bottoms um so that's all i would say i mean i don't really think it needs to be any more complicated
than that i think it's easy to sort of fill our minds with a thousand different charts and i have a
thousand different charts to talk about but at the end of the day at the end of the day i do think
you can you can kind of condense a lot of this stuff into a single risk metric to then use to
navigate the crypto verse rather than worry about everything else because i mean i think there's
something to be said about living your life right there's more to life than just investing
there's more to life than bitcoin right there's more to life than just crypto so why not just figure
out something to help you navigate it and it doesn't have to be this one right there's there's other
you can create your own risk metric uh basically just find something that looks like it oscillates
you know in a pretty well-defined range and then you can normalize it between zero and one
and then you can create your own risk metric right um but just you i would say use something
that allows you to to sort of look at it through a more quantitative perspective rather than the
emotions because imagine imagine you're right and we get a strategic reserve right imagine that you
know sometime this year trump says that there's a good chance the market would get a really good rally
at that point and there's no telling how high the market could go uh but i would say i would just
go back to the risk metric right if bitcoin is at 150k or 180k and we're at like 0.95 risk i don't care
what the narrative is i'm running for the hills like you said you have a thousand different charts i want
to know how you come up with all these charts and what are some weirdest charts that you've made
a lot of them are just my own interest right i mean like some of them are created by other people
right they're not all created by me there's one really interesting chart um so it's called it's
called roi bands so it kind of looks like this where you have these roi bands like you know 2x 4x 6x 8x
10x and so on and so forth basically what it does is that any at every price point
in the cycle it will tell you from how many how many days after that did it take for the market to
go up a certain amount right so if you bought the peak in 2013 then in order to 2x your money
you would have had to wait um
about 1113 days because you bought the top right um but what's really fascinating about this chart
as you get close to major tops the amount of time it takes to 2x your money drops off a cliff because
the market's going parabolic right so this is this is a really interesting chart because i always have a
hard time explaining it to people you know every time i post a video about it i'm like oh it's this
i still don't understand it um but you know here's a description and usage of it if people want to
pause the video and just read it but um i thought that was an interesting chart uh there's also some
other you know some other really interesting charts that you know that i've created throughout the years
um but that there's one tracking youtubers yeah that one's really interesting so uh if you look at
this one it's basically new youtube views to various crypto youtube channels you know when earlier when
we're talking about is this like the dot-com era when we're talking about like the qqq comparison
and one of the reasons i didn't think it was like the qqq is because you know the smp with respect to
the money supply is not at that level that would suggest that it is the dot-com era but the other
thing is that the market was more insane in 2021 like look how many more people were viewing these
youtube channels in 2021 right back then at some points these channels were averaging around
4 million views a day collectively this cycle anytime collectively these channels go up to 2 million
views they then come back down right so you could argue that while it might feel like 2021 to a lot of
people because bitcoin's going up the reason that that retail hasn't really returned like the same way
they were here in 2021 is because a lot of the altcoins that they hold are just bleeding back to bitcoin
right and so i think this really is a reflection of of the altcoin market and actually one way to visualize
that is if you look at this crypto indicator dashboard right we talked about you know price risk we talked
about on-chain risk we also have social risk right you can look at social risk and look at the last two peaks
for bitcoin right the social risk was really high look at it right now it's at 0.27 no one's here you know i mean like
i'm here you're here and and there's there's some people watching youtube but compared to 2021 this is nothing
like it it's uh it couldn't i mean it's so different than 2021 it to me it still looks like this right it looks like this
little rally in 2019 where it was basically a bitcoin only rally and the altcoin market which is bleeding
to bitcoin until the fed into quantitative tightening like 2021 people had nothing else to do
right so it's true we might not get that anymore it's true but we i mean what about 2017 i mean it got
to these highs in 2017 and it's not like we had a pandemic back then um you know you could look at
at a lot of different things i mean we we could justify it in any normal you know any any amount
of ways um but the reality and by the way charts like this are not necessarily representative of it
going back to a peak you could have a situation where it doesn't go back up there this cycle because
people are more concerned with inflation and other things and so they're not as able to get interested
in crypto because they're more worried about how are they going to pay for groceries than which meme coin
they should buy you know so it's not like there's a guarantee that it goes up here but i i would argue
that if it if the social risk does go back up there it's probably a major cycle top right um at which
point you would probably you know like let's say let's say we're looking at this chart and it's january
of 2026 and let's say it's at like 0.8 risk or 0.9 risk it's probably a good chance that we're about
to enter into a bear market because the i think the understanding of it is if everyone has already arrived
then who else can you sell to you know like if retails already come and they bought who are they
going to then sell to and once you reach that point then the market then undergoes a bear market but
again the only way that social risk is going to durably go up like it did over here i think is for
the fed to pivot to much looser monetary policy right i think that's the only way because until that time
um we just haven't you know anytime there's any level of social interest at all it just falls back
off because the altcoins just keep on uh bleeding back to bitcoin and you can actually see i mean
there's a there's a direct inverse correlation between social interest and bitcoin dominance
um we actually have a workbench on the website where you can look at you can basically load in
a lot of these indicators so that you can load in social risk um and then you can load in um
uh we're going to load in uh dominant bitcoin dominance without stable coins and what you'll
notice is that as the yellow line is dominance and the orange line is social risk right so as social
risk goes down and goes sideways bitcoin dominance goes up but as social risk goes up bitcoin dominance
goes down so in order to really see bitcoin dominance go down you need to see social risk go up the way you
get social risk to go up is for looser monetary policy to arrive and until that time you know it just
kind of stays down here last cycle it started to go up after the fed cut interest rates basically back
to zero and they flooded the money with they flooded the market with money how do you track social risk
is it google trends youtube views yeah so i i need to add a few things to it this is my uh my age is is
reflecting here because i don't really track tiktok and instagram but i know there's a lot of interest
on tiktok um but right now i'm basically tracking uh for the social risk it's five things so it's
these are all five but individually it is subscribers to various youtube channels right so new subscribers
uh views to youtube channels uh views to those same youtube channels uh various followers to crypto
analysts on twitter or x um various followers to exchanges on x and then various followers to layer
ones on x and so i basically take those five and then combine it into a single social risk metric
a lot of uh projects are buying followers yeah i know and actually you can you can see that but
i think that and actually we can go look at that chart it is true that they do that but usually it
like doesn't last forever and it just kind of gets drowned out wait there's a chart for this fake followers
not for fake followers but it can be pretty obvious if there's if there if if something if someone's running
like a marketing campaign right so like if you look at twitter followers to layer ones um you know
anytime you see really weird spikes it's probably because there's either a major event going on or
someone is is running a marketing campaign it doesn't mean necessarily that they're like buying bots it
could just mean that they're advertising on facebook or on um reddit or on you know any platform to get
new followers right which doesn't mean a legitimate way um but like if you go through some of these
companies you know like if you look at at i don't know which one cosmos doesn't really look that
abnormal right like this looks probably like a normal chart the major the major spikes are at where you get
big market sell-offs which seems reasonable if you look at at um uh what was it if you look at like
solana there was a huge spike during the fcx crash which makes absolute sense right i mean a lot of
people were worried that solana was just going to go to zero um but you know occasionally you'll look
at projects and you'll see some like random spikes like this you know and you're just like what's going
on and it's probably marketing um look at luna i mean look at that spike when it collapsed um so
occasionally you get like these weird spikes in the data that don't that aren't occurring at a major
low or a major high and so when that happens it's usually because of some marketing campaign um and
you could you could also see similar stuff in analysts but i'm not looking to pick any fights
right now so we're just going to stay away from that okay so let's say altcoin season is still coming
and i'm deciding what all coins to buy there are some um narratives for example restaking ai rwa
what else meme coins made in the usa all that what should i pick so i think the first thing is that
alt season doesn't start until eth bitcoin convincingly bottoms right eth bitcoin i think is sort of the
the bellwether of the altcoin market so and by the way i'm not i'm not avoiding your question i will get
to your question uh but by the way i mean last cycle eth bitcoin bottomed when qt ended right precisely
and also the other thing to consider um last cycle there was also the same trend line like that eth usd was
on it's on the sort of this uptrend and it was eth bitcoin bottomed exactly when exactly when eth usd
lost support right so eth usd lost support and then right away eth bitcoin bottomed right so if eth usd loses
support here you could argue that eth bitcoin would then pretty quickly bottom out right um and that
doesn't mean that eth usd couldn't struggle for a little while but ultimately i do think it would it
would go back up um so i think the first place you would start besides bitcoin is is probably ethereum
at the end of the day eth bitcoin below 0.03 i think is really low um and i know if you've been a solana
maxi for a couple years right everyone's just saying like eth is dead but as i showed earlier i mean the
sole bitcoin chart looks a lot like eef bitcoin just delayed two and a half years and the uh the
exuberance that a lot of solana holders spill is the same type of exuberance a lot of eth holders
spelt around the time of the merge and it did nothing but bleed since then so i would say what
you would want to what you would want to see is a double bottom you don't always get it right like in
2016 you didn't get a double bottom so it's not like you have to have it but i would look towards that
and and any altcoin narrative that you're looking at i would say forget about the narrative look at the
look at its bitcoin chart one of the reasons why and look i know xrp is is a hated coin by a lot of
people um but listen i i think that we're all here to make money we're not here to you know
get married to an altcoin you know a lot of people get married to an altcoin and the altcoin takes you
know more than half in the divorce right whenever it eventually crashes i would say try not to do that
and and try to just focus on these patterns and the thing that xrp bitcoin had back in november
was a double bottom right you can see a low and then a double bottom a few months later so that's
what you look for you don't look for the narratives because the narratives are going to be a dime a
dozen and there's going to be a thousand different influencers you try trying to sell it to sell you a
thousand different narratives but i would say look at their look at their lows on their on their bitcoin
pairs and see if they can come up with a double bottom and if they can then it usually means they're
going to get a big spike upwards so some altcoins have gone through that process solana went through
that process back in 2022 you know in 2023 right it went through that process already xrp just went
through that process a few months ago um eth bitcoin hasn't even put in its first low yet right so i don't
you know it's hard to know i mean i i wouldn't be that surprised if that's the low for e bitcoin or
close to it um but you know there's some other coins i mean you could look at like bnb bitcoin i've
sort of had my eye on that one i'm wondering if it's going to turn into a double bottom here um
it's not entirely clear yet but i would say if if a if a couple months go by and bnb bitcoin is still
holding this as support then it could be a double bottom it's not like it's impossible uh for that to be
the case but then other altcoins you know you look at like avax bitcoin and i've been pretty convinced
this one's going to bleed forever and it has and the reason is this structure here is a really bad
structure um where it has a low in the middle of a bull market and then another low later on
if it can't if it if this forms a lower high it usually just bleeds down and then breaks support
and the reason you know this pattern is really common like you can look at dash bitcoin from a prior
cycle which dash was a you know a relic from like 2017 it had a very similar structure right you had
this sort of low in the bull market and then a another low later on in in the in sort of the next
cycle and then got a bounce to a lower high and then eventually just bled and then now look what
it's done the last few years right so you want to avoid altcoins that are not double bottoming right
so you can see with dash bitcoin when it came down here in in 2020 it bottomed but then later on it
just broke support right it broke support and if it does that it's it's almost always a bad sign
you don't want to see it break support with eth bitcoin last cycle you want to see the the second
low be above the wick of the first low you don't want to see it take out that wick because if it takes
out that week that wick it suggests that it is still bleeding look at sole bitcoin when it bottomed
the second low did not take out the first wick it did not take it out so that's what you look for
so with bnb bitcoin right now if it goes below this wick then it's probably just going to keep
bleeding for a while if it can stay above
5 193 sats then it could be a double bottom really what you want to see you want to see the second low
low be no lower oftentimes you want to see it find support at the the candle body right there
if it goes but if it goes below this wick then it's still just likely going to keep on bleeding
so that's what i would look for right i look for altcoins that are are bottoming against bitcoin and
then putting in a double bottom but remember it's hard to do that right now there's only a few altcoins
that are doing it right i mean we just talked about a few in order to get the collective altcoin market to do
it you know it's kind of like buying a house right like the housing market right now sucks it doesn't
mean there's not some good deals out there just like crypto i mean the altcoin market sucks against
bitcoin it doesn't mean there's no there's not any good deals um if you look at all bitcoin pairs
right like last cycle they got this double bottom now they did eventually wick below that that was during
a parabolic bitcoin rally right i mean so yes they did technically go below it but it only lasted for like
two weeks and all usd pairs were going up right so i don't think anyone cared but in order to get
that to happen you probably need to see a shift in monetary policy so right now they're kind of few
and far between but as the year goes on you might you might get to the point where you start to see
more and more altcoins finding double bottoms against bitcoin so i would look towards that rather than
the narratives so um a lot of people probably bought the narratives like ai or like memes last year
because people are expecting this all queen season to come really soon and i assume a lot of people
hold their bags till now and like you said it's led to almost dead but how do you decide if i should
just cut my losses here i would say look at look at the altcoin on its bitcoin pair if it's bleeding
it's probably going to keep bleeding if it's putting in higher lows or holding its lows then it's probably
okay to hold on to um that's what i generally go with i would also say like 2025 is probably not like
the best time to make any rash decisions with all coins because it normally is the post having year
when all coins do start to do well against bitcoin right so it's probably going to happen at some point
this year but remember that in 2017 right last i think a lot of people are hoping that 2025 would just be
a repeat of 2021 and it's clearly not right it's clearly not um but if you go back to the 2017 cycle
um all bitcoin pairs got their last so so you remember we're talking about like 25 of bitcoin's
market cap right they hit that in november of 2017 so a lot of people were probably watching their
alts bleed to bitcoin for a while and then the last month of the year we got all season you know
and and whenever all season happens it only lasts usually for like three to four weeks you know i
mean you basically spend years watching all coins bleed back to bitcoin only for them to get this
major spike for three to four weeks and then it's over again for the next three to four years um
so you know i i don't really i wouldn't say that like making a rash decision in the post having year
is the the smartest decision right if you've if you've held the altcoin for three years and you've
watched it bleed back to bitcoin and you're you're now just thinking oh maybe i should cut my losses
and move on while my base case is that alts do go a little bit lower against bitcoin there's a good
chance that later on this year they they could they could get um you know a more sizable move and what
there's actually an indicator for that i mean there's uh if you look at at the the altcoin season index
that's actually an indicator that you can look at and and see like you know where the market is right now
i believe it's kind of like um i think it's kind of in between uh bitcoin season and all coins i don't
really think it's either one yeah right now the altcoin season index is 46.81 so it's a little closer
to bitcoin season than than all coin season so anytime it goes into the red shaded region up here it's
technically all season and anytime it's in the green shaded region it's bitcoin season
um but you can see that any moves that we've had near all season have been really short-lived
right so people keep thinking it's like the alt season that they remember from 2021
where it stayed up here for several months and it just keeps on being like a one-day wick and it
just comes back down um so in order to get a larger move up there like what you had in 2017 or 2021
you probably just need a pivot in monetary policy and you're probably going to get it at some point
this year three charts that you recommend newcomers to look at just three probably this one this is like
the total market cap of crypto with sort of like a logarithmic regression trend line fitted to it to
just kind of show you like what is the quote unquote fair value of the asset class i think it's
a really good way to visualize the boom and bust cycles right the bull markets and the bear markets
um and to try to keep people on track i think that's a good one i think that the other one i i think this
risk metric is really useful um to just try to identify like is the market heated or is it not
uh i think that's a really good one as far as a third one um maybe maybe just this maybe just the
roi from the bottom right i think that's a good one because i think like sometimes you know the market
gets like like last march the market got kind of heated got kind of carried away where it was well
above the prior two cycles and you can you can see that it had to basically bleed until the last two
cycles sort of caught up with it right um and the same thing happened the cycle before where it got
really far ahead of where it should have been and then it bled until that cycle caught up to it so
i think looking at this chart is probably one of the most helpful charts to look at to just try to
keep you on track with what's actually going on like sometimes it can feel like the cycle sucks for
bitcoin but you look at it and you're like well it's up over 6x from the low which is exactly the
amount it was up at this point in 2017 so why should we you know what's the big deal so but those three
charts anything else you would like to um recommend to newcomers or let's say people experiencing their
first cycle i would say just come up with a plan and stick to it and and don't change your mind
during major market events like you know when you get capitulations like we saw earlier this week
um or in august of last year or in april of last year when you get those big market events don't be the
person that's going to panic um have a plan and and and stick to it because if you if you are the
type of person that's going to panic you're gonna end up making a really bad decision whether it's
selling the bottom or buying the top and you're going to probably regret it so it's easier to come
up with plans during times in the market like this when the market's not moving and then you stick to
that plan no matter what right you don't change your mind a month from now based on what the market's
been doing because that's an emotional decision now i think you know when the market's not moving
we're more capable of making rational decisions right um when the market's moving that's where
the fomo and the emotions come in so make the decisions now and then stick to them later if you
want to explore the charts we mentioned today yourself um new users you can use promo code and
get 10 off today thank you so much for your time ben thanks for having me